How to Use PHP’s built-in Web Server

Deprecated since version 4.4: This article explains how to use the WebServerBundle to run Symfony applications on your local computer. However, that bundle is deprecated since Symfony 4.4 and will be removed in Symfony 5.0.

Instead of using WebServerBundle, the preferred way to run your Symfony applications locally is to use the Symfony Local Web Server.

The PHP CLI SAPI comes with a built-in web server [https://www.php.net/manual/en/features.commandline.webserver.php]. It can be used to run your PHP applications locally during development, for testing or for application demonstrations. This way, you don’t have to bother configuring a full-featured web server such as Apache or nginx.

Caution

The built-in web server is meant to be run in a controlled environment. It is not designed to be used on public networks.

Symfony provides a web server built on top of this PHP server to simplify your local setup. This server is distributed as a bundle, so you must first install and enable the server bundle.

Installing the Web Server Bundle

Move into your project directory and run this command:

1
2

|

$ cd your-project/
$ composer require --dev symfony/web-server-bundle

Starting the Web Server

To run a Symfony application using PHP’s built-in web server, run the server:start command:

1

|

$ php bin/console server:start

This starts the web server at localhost:8000 in the background that serves your Symfony application.

By default, the web server listens on port 8000 on the loopback device. You can change the socket passing an IP address and a port as a command-line argument:

1
2
3
4
5

|

# passing a specific IP and port
$ php bin/console server:start 192.168.0.1:8080

# passing '*' as the IP means to use 0.0.0.0 (i.e. any local IP address)
$ php bin/console server:start *:8080

Note

You can use the server:status command to check if a web server is listening:

1

|

$ php bin/console server:status

Tip

Some systems do not support the server:start command, in these cases you can execute the server:run command. This command behaves slightly different. Instead of starting the server in the background, it will block the current terminal until you terminate it (this is usually done by pressing Ctrl and C).

Using the built-in Web Server from inside a Virtual Machine

If you want to use the built-in web server from inside a virtual machine and then load the site from a browser on your host machine, you’ll need to listen on the 0.0.0.0:8000 address (i.e. on all IP addresses that are assigned to the virtual machine):

1

|

$ php bin/console server:start 0.0.0.0:8000

Caution

You should NEVER listen to all interfaces on a computer that is directly accessible from the Internet. The built-in web server is not designed to be used on public networks.

Command Options

The built-in web server expects a “router” script (read about the “router” script on php.net [https://www.php.net/manual/en/features.commandline.webserver.php#example-415]) as an argument. Symfony already passes such a router script when the command is executed in the prod or dev environment. Use the --router option to use your own router script:

1

|

$ php bin/console server:start --router=config/my_router.php

If your application’s document root differs from the standard directory layout, you have to pass the correct location using the --docroot option:

1

|

$ php bin/console server:start --docroot=public_html

Stopping the Server

When you finish your work, you can stop the web server with the following command:

1

|

$ php bin/console server:stop

Upgrading a Third-Party Bundle for a Major Symfony Version

Symfony 3 was released on November 2015. Although this version doesn’t contain any new features, it removes all the backward compatibility layers included in the previous 2.8 version. If your bundle uses any deprecated feature and it’s published as a third-party bundle, applications upgrading to Symfony 3 will no longer be able to use it.

Allowing to Install Symfony 3 Components

Most third-party bundles define their Symfony dependencies using the ~2.N or ^2.N constraints in the composer.json file. For example:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7

|

{
    "require": {
        "symfony/framework-bundle": "~2.7",
        "symfony/finder": "~2.7",
        "symfony/validator": "~2.7"
    }
}

These constraints prevent the bundle from using Symfony 3 components, so it makes it impossible to install it in a Symfony 3 based application. Thanks to the flexibility of Composer dependencies constraints, you can specify more than one major version by replacing ~2.N by ~2.N|~3.0 (or ^2.N by ^2.N|~3.0).

The above example can be updated to work with Symfony 3 as follows:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7

|

{
    "require": {
        "symfony/framework-bundle": "~2.7|~3.0",
        "symfony/finder": "~2.7|~3.0",
        "symfony/validator": "~2.7|~3.0"
    }
}

Tip

Another common version constraint found on third-party bundles is >=2.N. You should avoid using that constraint because it’s too generic (it means that your bundle is compatible with any future Symfony version). Use instead ~2.N|~3.0 or ^2.N|~3.0 to make your bundle future-proof.

Look for Deprecations and Fix Them

Besides allowing users to use your bundle with Symfony 3, your bundle must stop using any feature deprecated by the 2.8 version because they are removed in 3.0 (you’ll get exceptions or PHP errors). The easiest way to detect deprecations is to install the symfony/phpunit-bridge package [https://github.com/symfony/phpunit-bridge] and then run the test suite.

First, install the component as a dev dependency of your bundle:

1

|

$ composer require --dev symfony/phpunit-bridge

Then, run your test suite and look for the deprecation list displayed after the PHPUnit test report:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14

|

# this command is available after running "composer require --dev symfony/phpunit-bridge"
$ ./bin/phpunit

# ... PHPUnit output

Remaining deprecation notices (3)

The "pattern" option in file ... is deprecated since version 2.2 and will be
removed in 3.0. Use the "path" option in the route definition instead ...

Twig Function "form_enctype" is deprecated. Use "form_start" instead in ...

The Symfony\Component\Security\Core\SecurityContext class is deprecated since
version 2.6 and will be removed in 3.0. Use ...

Fix the reported deprecations, run the test suite again and repeat the process until no deprecation usage is reported.

Useful Resources

There are several resources that can help you detect, understand and fix the use of deprecated features:

Official Symfony Guide to Upgrade from 2.x to 3.0 [https://github.com/symfony/symfony/blob/2.8/UPGRADE-3.0.md]

The full list of changes required to upgrade to Symfony 3.0 and grouped by component.

SensioLabs DeprecationDetector [https://github.com/sensiolabs-de/deprecation-detector]

It runs a static code analysis against your project’s source code to find usages of deprecated methods, classes and interfaces. It works for any PHP application, but it includes special detectors for Symfony applications, where it can also detect usages of deprecated services.

Symfony Upgrade Fixer [https://github.com/umpirsky/Symfony-Upgrade-Fixer]

It analyzes Symfony projects to find deprecations. In addition it solves automatically some of them thanks to the growing list of supported “fixers”.

Testing your Bundle in Symfony 3

Now that your bundle has removed all deprecations, it’s time to test it for real in a Symfony 3 application. Assuming that you already have a Symfony 3 application, you can test the updated bundle locally without having to install it through Composer.

If your operating system supports symbolic links, instead point the appropriate vendor directory to your local bundle root directory:

1

|

$ ln -s /path/to/your/local/bundle/ vendor/you-vendor-name/your-bundle-name

If your operating system doesn’t support symbolic links, you’ll need to copy your local bundle directory into the appropriate directory inside vendor/.

Update the Travis CI Configuration

In addition to running tools locally, it’s recommended to set-up Travis CI service to run the tests of your bundle using different Symfony configurations. Use the following recommended configuration as the starting point of your own configuration:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20
21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29

|

language: php
php:
    - 5.3
    - 5.6
    - 7.0

matrix:
    include:
        - php: 5.3.3
          env: COMPOSER_FLAGS='--prefer-lowest --prefer-stable' SYMFONY_DEPRECATIONS_HELPER=max[total]=999999
        - php: 5.6
          env: SYMFONY_VERSION='2.7.*'
        - php: 5.6
          env: SYMFONY_VERSION='2.8.*'
        - php: 5.6
          env: SYMFONY_VERSION='3.0.*'
        - php: 5.6
          env: SYMFONY_VERSION='3.1.*'
        - php: 5.6
          env: DEPENDENCIES='dev' SYMFONY_VERSION='3.2.*@dev'

before_install:
    - composer self-update
    - if [ "$DEPENDENCIES" == "dev" ]; then perl -pi -e 's/^}$/,"minimum-stability":"dev"}/' composer.json; fi;
    - if [ "$SYMFONY_VERSION" != "" ]; then composer --no-update require symfony/symfony:${SYMFONY_VERSION}; fi;

install: composer update $COMPOSER_FLAGS

script: phpunit

Updating your Code to Support Symfony 2.x and 3.x at the Same Time

The real challenge of adding Symfony 3 support for your bundles is when you want to support both Symfony 2.x and 3.x simultaneously using the same code. There are some edge cases where you’ll need to deal with the API differences.

Before diving into the specifics of the most common edge cases, the general recommendation is to not rely on the Symfony Kernel version to decide which code to use:

if (Kernel::VERSION_ID < 20800) {
    // code for Symfony 2.x
} else {
    // code for Symfony 3.x
}

Instead of checking the Symfony Kernel version, check the version of the specific component. For example, the OptionsResolver API changed in its 2.6 version by adding a setDefined() method. The recommended check in this case would be:

use Symfony\Component\OptionsResolver\OptionsResolver;

if (!method_exists(OptionsResolver::class, 'setDefined')) {
    // code for the old OptionsResolver API
} else {
    // code for the new OptionsResolver API
}

Tip

There is one case when you actually can rely on the Symfony\Component\HttpKernel\Kernel::VERSION_ID constant: when trying to detect the version of the symfony/http-kernel component, because it is the component where this constant is defined.

Setting up or Fixing File Permissions

Symfony generates certain files in the var/ directory of your project when running the application. In the dev environment, the bin/console and public/index.php files use umask() to make sure that the directory is writable. This means that you don’t need to configure permissions when developing the application in your local machine.

However, using umask() is not considered safe in production. That’s why you often need to configure some permissions explicitly in your production servers as explained in this article.

Permissions Required by Symfony Applications

These are the permissions required to run Symfony applications:

The var/log/ directory must exist and must be writable by both your web server user and the terminal user;

The var/cache/ directory must be writable by the terminal user (the user running cache:warmup or cache:clear commands);

The var/cache/ directory must be writable by the web server user if you use a filesystem-based cache.

Configuring Permissions for Symfony Applications

On Linux and macOS systems, if your web server user is different from your command line user, you need to configure permissions properly to avoid issues. There are several ways to achieve that:

1. Using ACL on a System that Supports setfacl (Linux/BSD)

Using Access Control Lists (ACL) permissions is the most safe and recommended method to make the var/ directory writable. You may need to install setfacl and enable ACL support [https://help.ubuntu.com/community/FilePermissionsACLs] on your disk partition before using this method. Then, use the following script to determine your web server user and grant the needed permissions:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7

|

$ HTTPDUSER=$(ps axo user,comm | grep -E '[a]pache|[h]ttpd|[_]www|[w]ww-data|[n]ginx' | grep -v root | head -1 | cut -d\  -f1)
# if this doesn't work, try adding `-n` option

# set permissions for future files and folders
$ sudo setfacl -dR -m u:"$HTTPDUSER":rwX -m u:$(whoami):rwX var
# set permissions on the existing files and folders
$ sudo setfacl -R -m u:"$HTTPDUSER":rwX -m u:$(whoami):rwX var

Both of these commands assign permissions for the system user (the one running these commands) and the web server user.

Note

setfacl isn’t available on NFS mount points. However, storing cache and logs over NFS is strongly discouraged for performance reasons.

2. Use the same User for the CLI and the Web Server

Edit your web server configuration (commonly httpd.conf or apache2.conf for Apache) and set its user to be the same as your CLI user (e.g. for Apache, update the User and Group directives).

Caution

If this solution is used in a production server, be sure this user only has limited privileges (no access to private data or servers, execution of unsafe binaries, etc.) as a compromised server would give to the hacker those privileges.

3. Without Using ACL

If none of the previous methods work for you, change the umask so that the cache and log directories are group-writable or world-writable (depending if the web server user and the command line user are in the same group or not). To achieve this, put the following line at the beginning of the bin/console, and public/index.php files:

umask(0002); // This will let the permissions be 0775

// or

umask(0000); // This will let the permissions be 0777

Caution

Changing the umask is not thread-safe, so the ACL methods are recommended when they are available.

Symfony Local Web Server

You can run Symfony applications with any web server (Apache, nginx, the internal PHP web server, etc.). However, Symfony provides its own web server to make you more productive while developing your applications.

Although this server is not intended for production use, it supports HTTP/2, TLS/SSL, automatic generation of security certificates, local domains, and many other features that sooner or later you’ll need when developing web projects. Moreover, the server is not tied to Symfony and you can also use it with any PHP application and even with HTML or single page applications.

Installation

The Symfony server is part of the symfony binary created when you install Symfony [https://symfony.com/download] and has support for Linux, macOS and Windows.

Note

The Symfony binary is developed internally at Symfony. If you want to report a bug or suggest a new feature, please create an issue on symfony/cli [https://github.com/symfony/cli].

Getting Started

The Symfony server is started once per project, so you may end up with several instances (each of them listening to a different port). This is the common workflow to serve a Symfony project:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8

|

$ cd my-project/
$ symfony server:start

  [OK] Web server listening on http://127.0.0.1:....
  ...

# Now, browse the given URL, or run this command:
$ symfony open:local

Running the server this way makes it display the log messages in the console, so you won’t be able to run other commands at the same time. If you prefer, you can run the Symfony server in the background:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9

|

$ cd my-project/

# start the server in the background
$ symfony server:start -d

# continue working and running other commands...

# show the latest log messages
$ symfony server:log

Enabling PHP-FPM

Note

PHP-FPM must be installed locally for the Symfony server to utilize.

When the server starts it will check for common patterns like web/app.php, web/app_dev.php or public/index.php. If a file like this is found the server will automatically start with PHP-FPM enabled. Otherwise the server will start without PHP-FPM and will show a Page not found page when trying to access a .php file in the browser.

Tip

When an index.html and a front controller like e.g. index.php are both present the server will still start with PHP-FPM enabled but the index.html will take precedence over the front controller. This means when an index.html file is present in public or web, it will be displayed instead of the index.php which would show e.g. the Symfony application.

Enabling TLS

Browsing the secure version of your applications locally is important to detect problems with mixed content early, and to run libraries that only run in HTTPS. Traditionally this has been painful and complicated to set up, but the Symfony server automates everything. First, run this command:

1

|

$ symfony server:ca:install

This command creates a local certificate authority, registers it in your system trust store, registers it in Firefox (this is required only for that browser) and creates a default certificate for localhost and 127.0.0.1. In other words, it does everything for you.

Before browsing your local application with HTTPS instead of HTTP, restart its server stopping and starting it again.

Different PHP Settings Per Project

Selecting a Different PHP Version

If you have multiple PHP versions installed on your computer, you can tell Symfony which one to use creating a file called .php-version at the project root directory:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7

|

$ cd my-project/

# use a specific PHP version
$ echo 7.2 > .php-version

# use any PHP 7.x version available
$ echo 7 > .php-version

Tip

The Symfony server traverses the directory structure up to the root directory, so you can create a .php-version file in some parent directory to set the same PHP version for a group of projects under that directory.

Run the command below if you don’t remember all the PHP versions installed on your computer:

1
2
3
4
5

|

$ symfony local:php:list

  # You'll see all supported SAPIs (CGI, FastCGI, etc.) for each version.
  # FastCGI (php-fpm) is used when possible; then CGI (which acts as a FastCGI
  # server as well), and finally, the server falls back to plain CGI.

Overriding PHP Config Options Per Project

You can change the value of any PHP runtime config option per project by creating a file called php.ini at the project root directory. Add only the options you want to override:

1
2
3
4
5
6

|

$ cd my-project/

# this project only overrides the default PHP timezone
$ cat php.ini
[Date]
date.timezone = Asia/Tokyo

Running Commands with Different PHP Versions

When running different PHP versions, it is useful to use the main symfony command as a wrapper for the php command. This allows you to always select the most appropriate PHP version according to the project which is running the commands. It also loads the env vars automatically, which is important when running non-Symfony commands:

1
2
3
4
5
6

|

# runs the command with the default PHP version
$ php -r "..."

# runs the command with the PHP version selected by the project
# (or the default PHP version if the project didn't select one)
$ symfony php -r "..."

Local Domain Names

By default, projects are accessible at some random port of the 127.0.0.1 local IP. However, sometimes it is preferable to associate a domain name to them:

It’s more convenient when you work continuously on the same project because port numbers can change but domains don’t;

The behavior of some applications depend on their domains/subdomains;

To have stable endpoints, such as the local redirection URL for OAuth2.

Setting up the Local Proxy

Local domains are possible thanks to a local proxy provided by the Symfony server. If this is the first time you run the proxy, you must configure it as follows:

Open the proxy settings of your operating system:

Proxy settings in Windows [https://www.dummies.com/computers/operating-systems/windows-10/how-to-set-up-a-proxy-in-windows-10/];

Proxy settings in macOS [https://support.apple.com/guide/mac-help/enter-proxy-server-settings-on-mac-mchlp2591/mac];

Proxy settings in Ubuntu [https://help.ubuntu.com/stable/ubuntu-help/net-proxy.html.en].

Set the following URL as the value of the Automatic Proxy Configuration: http://127.0.0.1:7080/proxy.pac

Now run this command to start the proxy:

1

|

$ symfony proxy:start

Note

Some browsers (e.g. Chrome) require to re-apply proxy settings (clicking on Re-apply settings button on the chrome://net-internals/#proxy page) or a full restart after starting the proxy. Otherwise, you’ll see a “This webpage is not available” error (ERR_NAME_NOT_RESOLVED).

Defining the Local Domain

By default, Symfony proposes .wip (for Work in Progress) for the local domains. You can define a local domain for your project as follows:

1
2

|

$ cd my-project/
$ symfony proxy:domain:attach my-domain

If you have installed the local proxy as explained in the previous section, you can now browse https://my-domain.wip to access your local project with the new custom domain.

Tip

Browse the http://127.0.0.1:7080 URL to get the full list of local project directories, their custom domains, and port numbers.

When running console commands, add the https_proxy env var to make custom domains work:

1

|

$ https_proxy=http://127.0.0.1:7080 curl https://my-domain.wip

Note

Although env var names are always defined in uppercase, the https_proxy env var is treated differently [https://ec.haxx.se/usingcurl/usingcurl-proxies#http_proxy-in-lower-case-only] than other env vars and its name must be spelled in lowercase.

Tip

If you prefer to use a different TLD, edit the ~/.symfony/proxy.json file (where ~ means the path to your user directory) and change the value of the tld option from wip to any other TLD.

Long-Running Commands

Long-running commands, such as the ones that compile front-end web assets, block the terminal and you can’t run other commands at the same time. The Symfony server provides a run command to wrap them as follows:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16

|

# compile Webpack assets using Symfony Encore ... but do that in the
# background to not block the terminal
$ symfony run -d yarn encore dev --watch

# continue working and running other commands...

# from time to time, check the command logs if you want
$ symfony server:log

# and you can also check if the command is still running
$ symfony server:status
Web server listening on ...
Command "yarn ..." running with PID ...

# stop the web server (and all the associated commands) when you are finished
$ symfony server:stop

Docker Integration

The local Symfony server provides full Docker [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Docker_(software)] integration for projects that use it.

When the web server detects that Docker Compose is running for the project, it automatically exposes environment variables according to the exposed port and the name of the docker-compose services.

Consider the following configuration:

1
2
3
4

|

# docker-compose.yaml
services:
    database:
        ports: [3306]

The web server detects that a service exposing port 3306 is running for the project. It understands that this is a MySQL service and creates environment variables accordingly with the service name (database) as a prefix: DATABASE_URL, DATABASE_HOST, …

If the service is not in the supported list below, generic environment variables are set: PORT, IP, and HOST.

If the docker-compose.yaml names do not match Symfony’s conventions, add a label to override the environment variables prefix:

1
2
3
4
5
6

|

# docker-compose.yaml
services:
    db:
        ports: [3306]
        labels:
            com.symfony.server.service-prefix: 'DATABASE'

In this example, the service is named db, so environment variables would be prefixed with DB_, but as the com.symfony.server.service-prefix is set to DATABASE, the web server creates environment variables starting with DATABASE_ instead as expected by the default Symfony configuration.

Here is the list of supported services with their ports and default Symfony prefixes:

Service

|

Port

|

Symfony default prefix

MySQL

|

3306

|

DATABASE_

PostgreSQL

|

5432

|

DATABASE_

Redis

|

6379

|

REDIS_

Memcached

|

11211

|

MEMCACHED_

RabbitMQ

|

5672

|

RABBITMQ_ (set user and pass via Docker RABBITMQ_DEFAULT_USER and RABBITMQ_DEFAULT_PASS env var)

Elasticsearch

|

9200

|

ELASTICSEARCH_

MongoDB

|

27017

|

MONGODB_ (set the database via a Docker MONGO_DATABASE env var)

Kafka

|

9092

|

KAFKA_

MailCatcher

|

1025/1080 or 25/80

|

MAILER_

Blackfire

|

8707

|

BLACKFIRE_

You can open web management interfaces for the services that expose them:

1
2

|

$ symfony open:local:webmail
$ symfony open:local:rabbitmq

Or click on the links in the “Server” section of the web debug toolbar.

Tip

To debug and list all exported environment variables, run symfony var:export.

Tip

For some services, the web server also exposes environment variables understood by CLI tools related to the service. For instance, running symfony run psql will connect you automatically to the PostgreSQL server running in a container without having to specify the username, password, or database name.

When Docker services are running, browse a page of your Symfony application and check the “Symfony Server” section in the web debug toolbar; you’ll see that “Docker Compose” is “Up”.

Note

If you don’t want environment variables to be exposed for a service, set the com.symfony.server.service-ignore label to true:

1
2
3
4
5
6

|

# docker-compose.yaml
services:
    db:
        ports: [3306]
        labels:
            com.symfony.server.service-ignore: true

If your Docker Compose file is not at the root of the project, use the COMPOSE_FILE and COMPOSE_PROJECT_NAME environment variables to define its location, same as for docker-compose:

1
2
3
4
5

|

# start your containers:
COMPOSE_FILE=docker/docker-compose.yaml COMPOSE_PROJECT_NAME=project_name docker-compose up -d

# run any Symfony CLI command:
COMPOSE_FILE=docker/docker-compose.yaml COMPOSE_PROJECT_NAME=project_name symfony var:export

Note

If you have more than one Docker Compose file, you can provide them all separated by : as explained in the Docker compose CLI env var reference [https://docs.docker.com/compose/reference/envvars/].

Caution

When using the Symfony binary with php bin/console (symfony console ...), the binary will always use environment variables detected via Docker and will ignore local environment variables. For example if you set up a different database name in your .env.test file (DATABASE_URL=mysql://db_user:db_password@127.0.0.1:3306/test) and if you run symfony console doctrine:database:drop --force --env=test, the command will drop the database defined in your Docker configuration and not the “test” one.

SymfonyCloud Integration

The local Symfony server provides full, but optional, integration with SymfonyCloud [https://symfony.com/cloud/], a service optimized to run your Symfony applications on the cloud. It provides features such as creating environments, backups/snapshots, and even access to a copy of the production data from your local machine to help debug any issues.

Read SymfonyCloud technical docs [https://symfony.com/doc/master/cloud/intro.html].

Upgrading a Minor Version (e.g. 4.0.0 to 4.1.0)

If you’re upgrading a minor version (where the middle number changes), then you should not encounter significant backward compatibility changes. For details, see the Symfony backward compatibility promise.

However, some backwards-compatibility breaks are possible and you’ll learn in a second how to prepare for them.

There are two steps to upgrading a minor version:

Update the Symfony library via Composer;

Update your code to work with the new version.

1) Update the Symfony Library via Composer

The composer.json file is configured to allow Symfony packages to be upgraded to patch versions. But to upgrade to a new minor version, you will probably need to update the version constraint next to each library starting symfony/. Suppose you are upgrading from Symfony 4.3 to 4.4:

 1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

|

{
    "...": "...",

    "require": {
-         "symfony/cache": "4.3.*",
+         "symfony/cache": "4.4.*",
-         "symfony/config": "4.3.*",
+         "symfony/config": "4.4.*",
-         "symfony/console": "4.3.*",
+         "symfony/console": "4.4.*",
        "...": "...",

        "...": "A few libraries starting with
                symfony/ follow their versioning scheme. You
                do not need to update these versions: you can
                upgrade them independently whenever you want",
        "symfony/monolog-bundle": "^3.5",
    },
    "...": "...",
}

Your composer.json file should also have an extra block that you will also need to update:

1
2
3
4
5
6
7

|

"extra": {
    "symfony": {
        "...": "...",
-         "require": "4.3.*"
+         "require": "4.4.*"
    }
}

Next, use Composer to download new versions of the libraries:

1

|

$ composer update "symfony/*"

Dependency Errors

If you get a dependency error, it may mean that you also need to upgrade other libraries that are dependencies of the Symfony libraries. To allow that, pass the --with-all-dependencies flag:

1

|

$ composer update "symfony/*" --with-all-dependencies

This updates symfony/* and all packages that those packages depend on. By using tight version constraints in composer.json, you can control what versions each library upgrades to.

If this still doesn’t work, your composer.json file may specify a version for a library that is not compatible with the newer Symfony version. In that case, updating that library to a newer version in composer.json may solve the issue.

Or, you may have deeper issues where different libraries depend on conflicting versions of other libraries. Check your error message to debug.

Another issue that may happen is that the project dependencies can be installed on your local computer but not on the remote server. This usually happens when the PHP versions are different on each machine. The solution is to add the platform [https://getcomposer.org/doc/06-config.md#platform] config option to your

composer.json

file to define the highest PHP version allowed for the dependencies (set it to the server’s PHP version).

Upgrading other Packages

You may also want to upgrade the rest of your libraries. If you’ve done a good job with your version constraints [https://getcomposer.org/doc/articles/versions.md] in composer.json, you can do this safely by running:

1

|

$ composer update

Caution

Beware, if you have some unspecific version constraints [https://getcomposer.org/doc/articles/versions.md] in your composer.json (e.g. dev-master), this could upgrade some non-Symfony libraries to new versions that contain backwards-compatibility breaking changes.

2) Updating your Code to Work with the new Version

In theory, you should be done! However, you may need to make a few changes to your code to get everything working. Additionally, some features you’re using might still work, but might now be deprecated. While that’s fine, if you know about these deprecations, you can start to fix them over time.

Every version of Symfony comes with an UPGRADE file (e.g. UPGRADE-4.4.md [https://github.com/symfony/symfony/blob/4.4/UPGRADE-4.4.md]) included in the Symfony directory that describes these changes. If you follow the instructions in the document and update your code accordingly, it should be safe to update in the future.

These documents can also be found in the Symfony Repository [https://github.com/symfony/symfony].

3) Updating Recipes

Over time - and especially when you upgrade to a new version of a library - an updated version of the recipe may be available. These updates are usually minor - e.g. new comments in a configuration file - but it’s a good idea to keep your files in sync with the recipes.

Symfony Flex provides several commands to help upgrade your recipes. Be sure to commit any unrelated changes you’re working on before starting:

New in version 1.6: The recipes commands were introduced in Symfony Flex 1.6.

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8

|

# see a list of all installed recipes and which have updates available
$ composer recipes

# see detailed information about a specific recipes
$ composer recipes symfony/framework-bundle

# update a specific recipes
$ composer recipes:install symfony/framework-bundle --force -v

The tricky part of this process is that the recipe “update” does not perform any intelligent “upgrading” of your code. Instead, the updates process re-installs the latest version of the recipe which means that your custom code will be overridden completely. After updating a recipe, you need to carefully choose which changes you want, and undo the rest.

Screencast

For a detailed example, see the SymfonyCasts Symfony 5 Upgrade Tutorial [https://symfonycasts.com/screencast/symfony5-upgrade].